Betty Velasquez: and I will kind of
Speaker 2: Sure.
Betty Velasquez: [Clears throat] Since this is the first meeting of 2024,
I think it'd be appropriate for everyone to go around and just
introduce themselves and who they're with if that's okay.
We will start with Kiarra.
Kiara Gomez: Hey everyone, Kiara Gomez I'm with the
Migrant Farmworker Division of Colorado Legal Services.
Jennifer Rodriguez: Hi uh, Jennifer Rodriguez also with the
Farm Division of Colorado Legal Services.
Betty Velasquez : I'm Betty Velasquez, I'm with
Pledge Protect Farmer Worker Network.
Dan Waldvogle: And I'm Dan Waldvogle, Director
at Rocky Mountain Farmers Union.
Speaker 3: Morning everybody, [inaudible], Department of Agriculture.
[Coughs]
Betty Velasquez: Online, let's go with Hunter, start with you.
Hunter Knapp: Hunter Knapp, Development Director
for Project Protect Food Systems Workers.
Betty Velasquez: Kristina?
Kristina Rosett: Kristina Rosett, Colorado Department of Labor and Employment.
Betty Velasquez: I know it says Michael, but
it's not Michael, it's Eric I believe, right?
Speaker 4: You're muted.
Eric Yohe: I'm Eric Yohe with the Colorado Department
of Labor and Employment.
Betty Velasquez: Thank you, Griselda?
Griselda Varella: Hi my name is Griselda Varella,
I'm the Interpreter.
Betty Velasquez: Galen?
Galen Wallace: Galen Wallace, um farm worker with Tabbot Farms.
Betty Velasquez: I don't see anybody else on online is there
anybody else that I missed?
Speaker 4: We have David.
Joe Petrocco: Joe Petrocco, Petrocco Farms.
Betty Velasquez: Hi, Joe.
David Harold: David Harold,Tuxedo Farms.
Betty: Good morning David didn't didn't see you all. Thank you.
I think the first order of business we need
Kristina Rosett: sorry we have another CDLE attendee here. Kerri.
Betty Velasquez: Oh I'm sorry, I can't see everyone on
the screen.
Kerri Owen: Hi, Kerri, I'm with CDLE.
I administer the H2A program throughout the state.
Betty Velasquez: Hey, Kerri nice to see you.
Kerri Owen: Hey, nice see you.
Hunter Knapp: And I believe we have a member of the
public who just joined on Zoom as well.
Hunter Knapp: Trent Taylor?
Betty Velasquez: Trent did you want to introduce yourself?
Speaker 4: You're, you're muted Trent.
Trent Taylor: I'm Trent Taylor, I am with
Colorado Legal Services Migrant Farm Worker Division.
Betty Velasquez: Welcome, Trent.
Trent Taylor: Thank you.
Betty: So we do have the agenda up. Uh, the first order of business is the election or the appointment of officers for 2024.
We didn't do that at the last meeting. I think
it's appropriate since it's the first in-person meeting.
Jennifer: Well, I I nominate our current chairs to
continue, our last year's chair is to continue.
If I can do both.
I second that motion.
One at one at a time or what you use your preference?
Betty: We can do one at a time
Daniel: Either. I mean, I I'm more than happy to continue. Also,
I feel like I dropped the ball a fair amount so,
happy to as long as I'm not slowing things down,
um, more than happy, and been really happy to work with Betty.
Betty: Yeah.
We make a good team.
I think we can do together if you want.
Betty: Is there anybody else that's interested in the chair position?
Don't all jump at once. [Laughter].
If we have a nomination, do we have a second?
Speaker 5: Hunter I believe second
Betty: Hunter second, okay.
Anyone else?
Then call for your vote.
All in favor?
[Many voices] Aye.
Betty: Any opposed?
Okay, so Dan and I will co-chair for 2024.
Again, thank you for your confidence.
We need the appointment of the Wages Subcommittee Chair,
nominations for the Wages Sub Committee Chair.
Kiara: Um, I would like to nominate Jennifer Rodriguez. [Laughter].
Jennifer Rodriguez: Oh thank you.
Betty: We have a nomination of Jennifer. I will second that motion.
Any other and anyone else interested in that chair position?
Okay, hearing none, all in favor?
[Many voices] Aye.
Betty: Okay, any opposed?
Okay congratulations, Jennifer.
We now on to appointments of
the Labor Conditions Sub-committee Chair.
[Background conversation]
Betty: I will nominate Kiara as the [Kiara laughs]
no one's doing it
Jennifer: I know, like anyone else?
Betty: Well, I nominated Dan second. Any further discussion
or any other, anybody else interested in that chair position?
Okay all in favor?
[Many voices] Aye.
Betty: Any opposed?
Okay, congratulations, Kiara.
[Barely audible conversation] We confirmed on Friday and I sent a reminder this morning.
Daniel: [Clears throat] Yeah I guess the next thing on here was just to
kind of go over the have a review of the open meetings laws.
I actually don't know if we have anybody
that's prepared to speak on that or anything at this point.
Betty: Kristina, I think you had the open meetings you shared
that with us the first meeting that we had. Do you have that document handy?
Kristina: Um, not right at my fingertips but I could
probably find one.
Um, the one thing I would emphasize is trying to get stuff
in the shared Drive for and in advance of the meeting
so that the public is able to access um things like the agenda.
But yeah, let me look and see if I can find the
um resources that we initially shared too.
Betty: Thank you. [Clears throat].
Daniel: Yeah, maybe that goes back
into the Ag work the procedures discussion too.
Maybe we can have to talk a little bit more too,
for you know, if you and I have deadlines of a week before,
or the other chairs have a deadline for the week
before, or something like that, and we can get it in the drive and
because if not I'll wait until I'm driving up here
at every red stoplight to try to like add
Jennifer: that's safe
Daniel: Yeah yeah, right? I didn't rec [laughter].
Anybody have any other questions at this point? Or maybe we
can bookmark this for another time to discuss a little bit more
I think sunshine laws are always kind
of tricky to navigate and feel like we're being effective
um, while being compliant
but wanted to provide some space for discussion.
Betty: So for the agenda we we kind of struggled
with this because of the Sunshine Law um,
it's been a little diffic difficult to navigate
so I guess my question to the group is
What would be the pleasures? If we create a draft, send it out to everyone?
Or have Kristina or somebody send it out?
Or Aldo send it out to everyone and people add to it? Or,
What would be the best way to navigate the agenda?
Kiara: Oh because we can do like a shared Google doc, is that allowed?
Betty: I believe so. Kristina, is that allowed if we put it on the shared Drive?
Kristina: Yeah, I mean I again, I can't give
like specific advice about the law, but
that's what I would recommend is to just create a shared
drive and then as long as again it's in the shared folder,
it's accessible on our website
and then um can make edits to it.
Hunter: And I want to suggest creating those agenda documents
in that shared drive there will be a subfolder like this
for each of the meetings. So after this meeting,
I'll create the one for March
and then if we create just a shared Google
doc for the agenda
any communications should be
contained in that Google doc
and then uh as far as my understanding
of the open records laws
that will be open to the public the whole time.
Betty: so Hunter not to add any
more to your workload but would it be
would it be possible for you to add agendas for the
month just to create create the doc for
the and and then we can just add to it and
have one each subcommittee as well
Hunter: That is not a problem at all, I can definitely do that.
Betty: Would that be easier?
Hunter: With sort of a blank template agenda.
Jennifer: I think that makes sense.
I think the only modification I would suggest
is something along the lines,
like it's we put that as like a draft agenda,
right, because if everybody can add to it then maybe like at
some point or at the very beginning of each meeting we like
accept it or whatever. Just because, since
anybody can add it any time, it's like,
I don't know I feel like the person who's running the meetings
should still kind of go over and make sure that it's like
Betty: And it should be adopted, you know? Sounds good.
Kiara: You're right.
Jennifer: And procedurally that should.
Kiara: Well we can set like maybe a deadline like
this day before the meeting have all your input in
so that everyone knows that that's the last day to add and that gives the
chairs maybe enough time to review and prepare accordingly.
Betty: So procedurally, we will adopt or
we will um approve the agenda prior to the meeting.
Jennifer: Yeah, okay.
Betty: Okay that makes sense.
Jennifer: Prior to the meeting? Or it has to be prior, okay,
yeah like you said, okay yeah.
Daniel: No, that sounds good.
Betty: Thank you, Hunter.
Galen: And I, I, I recall kind of looking
at open meetings rules.
If it's just on like basic logistics
there can be some member-to-member
discussion, right?
I think since this will be on a shared doc, if it's open
to the public there can be some back and forth with comments,
uh in there as well but,
I think we'll still want to kind of strike that
balance of not having too much um
narrative necessarily within that document as we're
looking to to set it and we can always, you know,
add to the agenda actually to you know
at the beginning of the meeting we need to.
Betty: Okay.
Jennifer: Just because we can't see everybody who's on
can you let us know someone if um if you do see L will get on okay?
Hunter: Yeah, it'll ask for me to admit
Jennifer: Oh okay
Daniel: Alright, with that unless there's any further discussion on open
meetings I'll pass it back to to Betty for the next bullet point
Betty: We wanted to review the the statutes
but I don't know if that's in are we prepared to do that today.
Or do we want to move on to the let's set the the
the structure of the each subcommittee and
then we can go back? Or how do you want to do this?
Galen: Sure, yeah. And we can
we should have in the document you know at least
a a link to the to the bill itself
um I don't know how deep you know
how deep we want to go into
the review of our charge and you know
the different Provisions in there
Betty: I think I'd like to jump ahead to go
ahead and get the subcommittees set
and then we can go into okay what did we cover this
last year and then really get into the statute and
Galen: Okay. That sounds fine.
Betty: So for the wages subcommittee, who would be interested?
We have our chair.
Who would be interested and serving on that committee?
Trent: I will definitely plan
to serve on the committee and be
at those subcommittee meetings every week.
Are there any other responsibilities attached
Jennifer: Oh um well no just I think to go and participate, right?
Um I mean at this point, unless we, does, like, I mean - As
we go, there might be certain things that people can, you know
take on, like some particular component but at this point, no.
Joe: I'll serve on sub-comittee.
Betty: Joe? Yeah.
Daniel: I plan on making both of them.
Galen: Same here
Kiara: I do too
[Inaudible]
Galen: That was Galen.
Jennifer: Well, all of us; Gayen, Betty, and Dan.
Betty: Dan, Kiara.
So that everybody?
Jennifer: Pretty much, except for David. What about David?
He's here, right? Yes yeah.
David: I'll I'll do what I can. I, my, I'm, I'm really frustrated -
my  time here is likely limited um
I've been drafting a letter uh of resignation slash
frustration to both the Governor and Kate.
Um, really feeling like this is a
waste of my time uh and um
yeah, I'll I'll leave it at that. But I I'm, I'm still a member
and I'll I'll be here when I'm here and we'll we'll see how that goes.
Betty: Labor Conditions? Dan do you want to take
that one? Sub-commmittee members?
Kiara: Yeah um anyone interested in signing up for the
labor conditions subcommittee I think Dan mentioned he'd be on both
Galen: Galen said that too.
Jennifer: I'd like to be on it too.
Kiara: Galen, Jen. Okay.
Anyone else for labor conditions? I think maybe
Hunter said both but I might have heard wrong.
Hunter: I did yes that's correct.
Joe: I'll do it.
Kiara: Joe, thank you. Okay.
Betty: I think that's everybody.
Kiara: Dan, Betty, Jennifer, Hunter, and Joe.
Perfect.
Jennifer: Just need to find out for my little I guess.
Betty: Yeah
Should we pull up the report and see what
we ended up with on the recommendations and move forward?
Daniel: Yeah. And at some point, I would like to maybe speak a little
bit to I have a feeling I've had some the same frustrations that David has had
um around I'm still a little confused
of the role of the report and
um the utility of it, and you know
are there things as a committee we could do to
to make sure that you know the work we put
in is um is a resource for our uh legislature and such.
And we're not just working in our seven
person backing or whatever we have here.
Daniel: And Kristina, you have a hand up.
Kristina: Yeah and not to go off topic, I just
wanted to let you guys know I had a couple
updates on things you asked for from
last time and wanted to
give a you know an introduction for the folks
from CDLE that are um new members to this meeting. So
um just whenever you want to fit
me into the agenda um call on me for that.
Betty: Now's a good time Kristina just go ahead and jump in.
Kristina: Okay um so as I I think I mentioned last time um I'm have um Eric Yohe here.
He'll be taking on the liaison role while I'm out on maternity leave.
So likely he'll be the face that you see
the next few months
and if there's any like logistical stuff
that you guys are discussing
you can continue to you know keep me on the
emails but add him in as well so he can help out.
I've given him kind of the background about the like interpreter,
the posting of the meeting schedule, and our website that kind of stuff
so should be good there. I also have Kerri Owen
here. I invited her after
there was an ask last time for kind of follow-up about
the status of the prevailing practice and wage surveys
and she was able to attend today so I just
invited her to to speak on that.
Another couple things:
There was talking talk about the wage calculator that CDA puts together or puts up on their worker
Services Program website and we worked with them to get a 2024 updated one so
you'll find that on the CDA's website
on the bottom the link that I
just put in the chat title wage calculator.
It's updated for 2024.
And hearing kind of the discussion last time we're also working on updating
that calculator so that there's another feature to
using your the number of employees you have this
year versus last year and during different seasons to
determine if you're small or highly seasonal so stay tuned for
resource on that. And then the other
piece was um oh a couple other things:
We also are working on, at your suggestion, a template notice for highly
seasonal employers to provide to employees so again
more to come. And then finally in the subfolder for the for today's meeting
you'll find a copy of the translated committee report into Spanish -
a PDF and a Word document.
So if you have questions on any of those kind of specific things I ran through we can
go through them but if there's time for Kerri to to chime in it might be nice to to
get her so she can get on her way for the rest of the day.
Kerri: Yeah thank you Kristina. So I just wanted
to give a quick update.
I know we talked about surveys and how they've
been in in works for quite a bit now. So
we finalized the employer practice survey so
I incorporated your guys' suggestions. I know you had,
Kristina had emailed some suggestions of questions
to ask so we incorporated that.
I had sent out the survey to a couple of my
colleagues at different state agencies just to get
who work with Ag employers to get an idea
of you know how does this look and
kind of got on the on the subject of redundancy and duplication.
So it seems that there are already some surveys out there to
Colorado producers and and Ag employers
so for the sake of redundancy and duplication I discovered I talked to USD and we
discovered we're allowed to partner with state agencies to conduct these inspections
and I know for example let's say CSU extension,
they conduct surveys to a Ag employers and
producers and again I know how
as an Ag employer or producer having to do surveys in general you
know is just takes a lot of time and then having to do surveys that are
the same questions as another survey you just took is you know not
very highly likely that they're going to complete those surveys.
So we're actually now going to pivot and even though we've completed these
surveys, we're pivoting to work with CSU extension hopefully in a collaboration of
just incorporating the surveys that they've already created
to include some of the requirements that are needed
specifically for the H2A questions in the surveys
to disseminate the surveys through CSU. So that's just a very
early stage right now. I know that my point of contact is
gearing up for his conference at the end of the month,
that's happening the 28th the CFGA conference, so
he's pretty busy so we plan on
meeting early March to get this going.
It just makes more sense to have an agency who has that
experience that has been doing it consistently
to collaborate with CDLE on these surveys
since like I said we don't want to send out multiple surveys to growers and
producers that has the same questions as surveys that just took from a different agency.
So we want to eliminate that duplication and redundancy.
But I still plan to include all the suggestions and things that you guys
you know submitted to include in those surveys that hopefully we're going to collaborate with CSU on.
And that's where we're at.
Jennifer: yeah can I ask a question Kerri?
Kerri: Of course
Jennifer: Um, so just to clarify, so when you talked about redundancy
so if there's like similar questions in your survey that are
currently in the the survey that us or CSU extension is doing
your you're not taking it out of your survey you're you're just
are you combining your survey with the CSU extension survey?
Kerri: Right good question. I think so.
Yeah no that's a great question and I
think that this is
very preliminary so I think that's what we're going to
discuss in March to figure out is it something that
is it going to have the face of CSU extension on on these surveys
and we're just incorporating our questions into that?
Or, is it just going to be a brand new survey that has you know the
that's from the Department of Labor but that CSU
extension is helping with? So I'm not quite sure yet.
Like I said it's very preliminary
But so, also, I was made of where too and I just want to make sure - Was there a survey
created, did this committee create a survey as well?
Or was that a different committee that created a survey?
Because I got word that a committee, an Ag committee was also created a survey.
So I just want to also make sure you know somebody else
is doing things that I'm not overstepping or
the the duplication of anything like that wasn't this committee.
Betty: The questions we came up with?
Jennifer: Right the questions we had for you.
Kerri: Oh that's just the question that you - Oh okay okay so maybe that
maybe they were just they misunderstood
because they telling me that there was a whole other
survey and I was like well I don't think so
Daniel: Kerri, this is Dan Woldvogle, and there is and there is another survey that
Rocky Mountain Farmers Union with um
the Colorado employee ownership office.
Kerri: okay
Daniel: and I believe another partner or so have been working on
um uh we've been developing a pilot for an employee owned Cooperative
um uh for folks that would provide Ag labor
and there has been kind of a survey circulating out there for that. Maybe that's
I think yeah so as as you as discussions happen in March if there's ways that we can
get any of that important information answered through a single
survey we'd be more than happy to
Kerri: I I think that's best
Daniel: I ownership office but yeah.
Kerri: Yeah I think that if we have you know again the capacity in
which you guys can work with different state agencies
like I just found out that you know Department of Labor
can work with other state agencies to to implement these surveys
so I mean again for the sake of not sending duplicates to to
to producers and having them answer a bunch of questions
if we could create a survey that is is you know centralized that'd be great but
at least for the H2A program requirements of having to do these surveys
that is our next step is is actually going to Pivot and see if we
can work with CSU who already again has the experience, already has
kind of a process for for creating and and implementing these surveys. So, again March
beginning of March that's what we're looking at to to get that processing.
Jennifer: I, thank you, I I was just trying to confirm, because I know your-
the mandate for the survey, I think it goes beyond the H2A program right, for the state
to do these prevailing wage surveys, um but want to make sure
that the whatever mandate that you all have to do it
like, if you're if even if you're combining it with the CSU extension one,
that it's still going to be in compliance with the
Kerri: Absolutely, yeah. So yeah we have yeah we have to have like
certain questions and things, you know. I mean the prevailing
the employer practice survey is pretty open it's flexible to include
whatever you know we just we just want to we have to make it
relate to the H2A program, right? So subsistancesubsistence, reimbursement, travel reimbursement,
that kind of thing. You know, do you provide that? What are what is your
kind of practice surveys as an Ag employer so we can effectively see how the h2a program should be ran, right?
Um the the pra, the wage surveys are more specific, you know, they do definitely have those specific questions that we have to
abide by, but the employer practice survey is pretty open. But the only from my I mean the only
mandate that I get it from is through the H2A program. You know, it's through my
foreign labor certification grant that tells me I need to do the surveys.
So I don't know if it's listed anywhere else. It might be, but specifically for the H2A program
it's part of that forign labor certification program that we do the surveys.
Jennifer: Got it. So it's the the prevailing practice survey that's going to be done at
the beginning of March, and the wage survey is different timeline.
Kerri: Well, so I I I want to talk about both I want to see if if CSU can do
both, I mean might as well right if if if they're willing to do these surveys
Um so I the conversation in March is going to be surrounded for both.
would be both the employer practice survey and the Wage survey.
Joe: There is a small questionnaire that might be presented at our Colorado
Fruit and Vegetable Association Annual Meeting, it'll be interactive.
So it kind of be an in-person thing only done at the meeting itself um.
It's just for producers only and how the laws affected our operations and so forth, but that's
all it focuses on. It doesn't really focus on any of the points that you just mentioned so.
It was put together by this committee
Kerri: Okay and so so those are the questions that we were talking about that you guys had
suggested to incorporate into the Sur into the survey that I was creating correct?
Or is that completely different a different survey?
Jennifer: I think he's talking about a different survey.
The one that he's doing it, the one that they're doing at their conference?
Kerri: Oh did you say it was it was created by this committee though, Joe? Sorry.
Joe: Well, I thought it was. Yeah it was just a
short list of questions that was passed by us.
Jennifer: Right, oh you're right right right. The same questions we sent to you.
Kerri: Yeah and I I okay yeah I mean, I I can't you know if if anybody
else wants to create surveys different agencies I mean that's
you know that that's fine, but I you know this is just specifically for
the H2A program that I'm hopefully we'll work with Adrian Card on.
I mean he's the one
Joe: Yeah Adrian will be doing this yeah okay
question and answer on that short
one it's not I don't think.
Kerri: Okay. So maybe we can include that if if if that's already being
implemented in the data that we get. But yeah,
so this is all this is all like preliminary like
I said. I'm meeting with Adrian at the beginning
of March to go over this process of collaborating
with CDLE and CSU on these surveys, but the whole
point is to you know not duplicate in in in these
surveys you know to make sure that the producers
aren't getting overwhelmed with the same kind of
questions and the same kind of surveys. So
hopefully we can streamline it that's the goal.
Daniel: Yeah I think the overall question too is
just how do we actually get trusted information
from Ag workers is the biggest riddle, so I mean
maybe that's another area of focus that we can
continue to explore this coming year or too of
how do we build the cannon for how we can agree
on what we accept as far as you know really being
able to truly hear the worker voice is I think the
biggest goal here.
Jennifer: Well then to get to get it out
to all workers right to the yeah to not the the
small percentage of just H2A workers,
Daniel: or potentially coerced or whatever it
Jennifer: Right to just have it more broad.
Kerri: Well yeah so the employer practice survey
and the and the prevailing wage surveys are not
for workers they're for the employers and it's
for all Ag employers because they're trying to
see how does normal Ag compare to the H2A
program, right? And are they similar and is the
H2A program running effectively compared to just
non H2A Ag work? So that that's the focus of of of
of the goals of or sorry of the surveys through
the H2A program. So I don't know if if that's in
line because it doesn't go to workers, it just
goes to employers.
Daniel: Yeah along that line, Kerri, just
for my information do it does the prevailing
wage survey and other information you gather
does that help inform the the adverse effect wage rate?
Kerri: absolutely
Daniel: Yeah so that's is that
part of this one and the same or is it? Okay
Kerri: No that's exactly it so part of that those those
the prevailing wage surveys is to help determine
the appropriate aare for for Colorado or for other
states. So, but the thing is is that we have to
have enough responses for it to matter like if
we only receive two responses I I wouldn't even
be able to submit them it wouldn't be enough data
to for them to look into that so I mean that's
why streamlining it and not duplicating you know
these surveys to hopefully get these employers
to respond you know to to a survey is key but
yeah it does it does it absolutely impacts how
the H2A program is is run. including the program
requirements of what you know the employer has to
do with reimbursement, um travel and then the the
wage. So it's it's key these these surveys are
key for over Ag um employers for especially for
H2A program but
Daniel: So what I'm hearing is that in
order to get more responses and have less survey
fatigue your hope is to kind of combine a few of
these different surveys to have one concise clear
way to really try to get as much information
as possible. This survey, let's say may have 20
Questions. 10 may just have to do with you know the
essential questions you need for H2A, I'm assuming
that the other 10 cannot inform what you need out
of H2A because those questions are pre-ordained as
far as what affects adverse wage rate a-word. Because the
reason why I ask is I know there's been a lot of
discussion of how do we reform the a-word survey so
it's more accurate when it comes to you know job
classifications and other things especially for
a state like Colorado where if you have a small
crew you might have folks doing a lot of different,
everybody's a skilled worker, but you might have
folks doing different skills all in kind of
the same smaller group. Does that make sense
as a question?
Kerri: Yeah and um so and again I I can't
answer that fully I just because I haven't had the
conversation yet with with CSU to figure out, but
I mean the idea would be to streamline, I mean that
is the idea to. Now I don't know if incorporating
other agencies surveys onto this one surveys is
the route that we would go, or if it just would
be a separate like this is CDLE's you know survey
because this is specifically for the program
requirements that I'm just collaborating with CSU
to do it through. Um so I don't know yet, but but
that that's something that I will keep in mind and
bring up on what makes sense um going forward with
with the surveys.
Daniel: Okay so yeah I I guess what I'm
trying to drill down to is your questions are your
questions and those are what inform your specific
yes H2A needs if we are adding other questions
that's just to get broader information in general
for I would back the a right I would incorporate
that into my data to send a USDOL right if it's
not relevant to the specific questions pertaining
to like H2A and how it affects the H2A program I
mean it could be included but it's not going to
be it's not going to be anything on data that I
would submit to USDOL it would just be the specific
questions that we have regarding h2a and AG yeah
perect can you share the timeline I guess as far
as so if it's completed in March like what is the
like when does it go out and then when do you need
have responses by and then when is the information
so USL doesn't really require like specific time
frames like oh you have to have surveys done by
this time it's just throughout you know the
year when you can get them done get them done
um so ideally I would like to have everything at
least implemented in survey sent out by July one
um that would be ideal to to have to have that
at least completed and sent out by July one and
again I don't know the process this is something
that's extremely new I don't know how long that
takes and if we are working with CSU what you
know their availability and things look like um
but ideally that is the the time frame we're
looking at how are they going to be sent out
is it going to be electronic or paper or you know
sometimes those mail official mail type of ballot
you know you get it seems like you'll get farmers
and producers to respond better when it's looking
more official in a paper form I know it's more
expensive but that's a great question I think
that's something we'd look at um I you know I'd
want to I'd want to get experience of people who
who work with people completed surveys of of what
is the most yeah popular way that producers would
respond if that is electronically or if it's
physical I mean I don't see why we couldn't do
both oh it's just yeah both would be good it's
just you I'm sure David could attest to this
emails we get so many right to 100 a day and we're
skipping through them and junking so many that it
especially July 1 you tend to pass them over so
do so does our administrators so um when you get
a paper one you almost feel like you're obligated
to do it okay that's great feedback thank you
Joe that's all I had if anybody doesn't if there's
any other questions thank
you Kerri yeah thank than
K so how do you all feel about going back up
to the subcommittee structure and the areas of
focus possibly pulling up the report and with
the recommendations we said you start talking
about the recommendations for 2024 some of
the topics that we wanted to tackle in 2024
uh Hunter can you pull up the final report and
the record with the recommendations if that's
the way the group wants to go at this point
yeah I mean if if possible I might like to
talk a little bit about the report itself
yeah before we talk about next steps with
it you know pulling up the statute you
know it says that we are to um where is
it you know by January 1 the advisory
committee shall report its progress
findings and legislative recommendations
to you know the two committees and I know
we're technically doing that by emailing
it to the two committees but I will say
that with the rush of the legislative
session um it's been my impression that
this isn't necessarily taking up a you know this
it's not necessarily making the splash maybe that
we would like I get I think or at least that
I would potentially like as as contributing to
this and I wonder if it makes sense for us to
request a a hearing to actually report things
or if we want to even though maybe we deliver it
in January maybe we invite the Committees to an
inperson meeting somewhere in the state you know
on a farmer ranch with a workers and and other
employers and stuff in June or something after
the session I I'd love to just kind of explore
a little bit of what our utility is and if do we
have control to kind of determine how we want to
report this out and and stuff because I think
if we're doing this work we do want to inform
the legislature and the administration and uh uh
and including our you know our Regulators as well
you know the I think this type of work is really
valuable for Ru making and everything else so I'd
maybe like to just invite a little bit of time for
discussion there if we want to talk any more about
that Dan my my take and and you were ready tell
me to shut up whenever you want uh's that I'm
kidding is uh the the way the bill was written
uh we had a business in uh whatever it was called
committee tell uh essentially the Senate and AD
committee we're going to we're going to do this
and they're going to report not back to us we're
the ones who care enough to write the legislation
but we don't care enough to check back in in
the future somehow they deemed it useful to
form a a group um but have them then report so
uh we've got Senate uh and house ad committees
that didn't even ask for us to exist to begin
with who were required to write a report to um
um I don't know I'm I've learned a lot about
politics since Senate Bill 2187 um and and how
our government functions but I've I've been
thinking a lot lately that um we we've come
we've uh got together and and uh spent a lot of
time and we produced something pretty useless
in many ways from a lot of standpoints uh anyway
uh and then we put that out and from what I know
uh through hearsay but um the the a committees
um have have no uh awareness of his existence
um I've I've spoken with legislators who said
they wanted to talk more with me who said they
really care um legislatur who were part of
the sponsorship of the bill and yet there's
no engagement there's been um very very little
use gotten from what we provided um and I you
know looking at a different perspective which
I still don't understand well but the governor
ultimately signed the bill and said Yep this
is useful for us and we have have cdle and CDA
staff and public funds going to to this committee
and I I really feel that we're all as a society
we're wasting our own time but we're wasting
taxpayer dollars having uh Aldo and Christina
and Eric Etc support us when when ultimately we're
we're just kind of dead in the water and it's uh
I don't know how we change it I don't know what
we do but it it is extremely frustrating to sit
here um and uh and and feel like just it
it's an absolute waste of time with zero
Effectiveness well I was wondering if we
couldn't go I was wondering why didn't two
or three of us get together or where we
requested to go and deliver the report in
person and that way we could be there during
the ACT Committee hearing and be available for
question and answer at least you know maybe
one producer one employee two or three of of
the rest of us uh go there in person and be
there and one of us deliver the the report
in person that way question and answer
from the egg committee or whoever else
might be there could we could do that it
seems to be more effective that way in the
Deliverance yeah I think that's an option
this goes to four committees it goes to
the ab Committee in both Chambers and it goes
to business labor and Tech Committee in both
Chambers so it would need to be kind of like
what when they have Smart act hearings where
they have you know a number of committees together
I don't think it's out of the question to request
a special hearing to discuss a labor in Colorado
um and I think either the chairs you know the two
chairs and the two subcommittee chairs could
present the full committee could present I do
think it could get a little challenging if all
of a sudden they're putting together a number
of experts and bringing in people and really
politicizing things but at the same time I do
think personally I think it's valuable to to
have these discussions as we move forward to
evaluate what's working and what's not what needs
to be changed I think that was kind of the goal
of this committee um originally was to provide
ongoing recommendations and findings um so it's
I don't think it's out of the question I just I
think there's maybe some pitfalls to avoid too
right and maybe that's a summer you know maybe
that's scheduled as an interim summer committee
but then that then all the people involved
in ager a little busy that time here too but
yeah I mean I I guess I have questions about how
how we do that I guess how that would be done it
would have to be formal because it would have
to be as a committee or speaking on behalf of
the committee not as an individual yeah exactly
and so everybody comes here with their own ideas
or you know agendas or thoughts or opinions and
stuff and so if we were going to be presenting
to any of those committees on behalf of this
yeah I think it would just be tricky and how
how that would be done but I imagine there's some
kind of protocol right when they do want to hear
from committees I just maybe you're more familiar
with that that no it's a good point and I there's
got to be something you like take a look at
the Colorado River drought task force they
met all summer long they made recommendations
I'm pretty sure they had a hearing on it if I
recall did they yeah see I'm just not familiar
with what the options are so that's something
we can explore because I agree that like we want
to avoid splintering off and all kind of because
I could I could take the this report down right
now and totally Advocate based on my organization
and that's not going to do the committee a favor
that's going to be our agenda you know so I think
there's got to yeah that's why I thought maybe a
mix of us it would be more effective because you
know when we're all there together we're there as
a committee and it's more about uh in that sense
us working together and instead of us working as
individuals and for our own companies we're doing
our job that we accepted to do and this committee
um so for me it's different you know if I was
there with with with with Dan and Jennifer and
and and Hunter and we were there in person doing
it we would I would not be as you know animate or
vocal as I am as when I'm there as an individual
I'd be as a Committee Member as this Committee
Member and be reflecting the the findings that
are here in our report more than what I would
be doing as an individual um then if there was
any question and answer we could answer them as a
group uh that's just kind of the way I feel about
it sounds like maybe be before our next quarterly
we can do some research and present back just
kind of how this works for other type of
task force advisory committees um best
practices how's that sound I it's a great
idea yeah I think that's a great idea and I
would definitely appreciate your expertise in the
political realm Dan in sort of figuring out how
these sorts of things are normally conducted how
we could schedule one um you sort of alluded to
the challenges with a July timing for this sort of
meeting um but we could start to plan it so we're
ready um in terms of presenting some substantial
recommendations hopefully with this next
report we'll do thank you Dan for
taking you had other thoughts so I guess yeah
I guess that's maybe that's the end of this
discussion unless anyone else wants to mention
anything on just the the document we created
what what we want to do with that instead of I
mean if I'm being clear like last year's work
what we want to do that compared to what we
want to do this coming year is there any more
discussion on ways we might want to report out on
on the report itself or do we want to wait until
we do some research and I have a question that's
kind of related to that what you're saying but
also the last Point like how do we learn what the
feedback is if any to our report I mean I guess is
that one of the things you're figuring out like
because we make these recommendations and I yeah
I realize some of them are there's nothing to go
with but some of them you know we're saying like
you should do a study you should do this and this
and like how do we what is the process in which
we find out they're like yeah no that's a great
idea but we're not we don't have the money for
this or we need more information about this like
seems like and so I don't know if that's part of
what you were going to be looking into or if not
like maybe that's something that we can add to it
right because like what yeah what were the what
was the response to this you know was it like
yeah and maybe it was just like nothing because
there yeah they're like okay thanks but if it was
like there was certain comments or criticisms
or request for more information or guidance or
whatever like that would be really helpful but so
maybe that's Christina I guess that's a question
for you you submitted the report did you get any
feedback or do we do we know how we would hear
any feedback I shared it with our legislative
leis on um so I can ask her if there's like any
process for that um but yeah she's the one that's
directly in contact with those committees thank
you she's going to ask the legislative Le
person okay and then I guess along the line
of procedures too I'd love to just have a little
bit of discussion there was an email that kind of
circulated for uh potentially bringing inviting
Ally Hill to present and there was from what I
recall a little um discussion on just process how
we how we um how to we agree who we're going to
bring in for presenting at meetings maybe open it
up for discussion there if we're kind of setting
up some procedures that we're all comfortable
with to make sure that we're um working
together yeah that was my comment and I just
thought we needed like a group consensus like
we do like in our subcommittees just to make
sure everyone was on board and I didn't know
if we could do that via email which is why
I suggest about it here but I don't know
if I super formal it's like everyone agrees
with it I think as long as everyone agrees
on at this committee I think we're okay and it
was Joe or gayen who sent the email right the
original one was David I believe you suggested
inviting her to the meeting but yeah I feel like
we can't really do that in email because of
the Sunshine Law like we have to have those
discussions here or like in a public
forum and make those decisions
right is that right yes yes as long as but I mean
if we have a public open Google Drive where we're
setting an agenda couldn't somebody recommend
inviting her and on the agenda we all accept the
agenda but not the email yeah right yeah I think
that's what you're talking about setting up a a
formal public process for having those discussions
yeah right so David you're the one who recommended
Ali Hill initially did you want to talk a little
bit about that and we can have that discussion
here and then come to a consensus or I I would
just argue back to the procedure topic that I
don't think were prohibited from working outside
of these meetings we if if we all said yeah okay
let's let's hear from Ali Hill in an email let's
invite her and we upload that that to the to the
shared document we are right we are not restricted
to only doing our work um once a month right we
where there's no nowhere in the legislature law
does it say you meet once a month we decided that
we could meet once a year we could meet once a
day we could meet once an hour uh we can email
we can get together we just have to do it in front
of the public and so um if if we want to hamstring
ourselves and say well we'll only do anything
when we're all here that that's a a procedural
thing of our own choosing if I'm not mistaken um
and and so be it um but um that that topic that
that specific to Dan's let's talk about procedure
I think we need to resolve before we talk about uh
Aly go ahead H yeah I was just gonna say
that I agree with sort of your framing of
the potential for emails for things like
the invitations um I do think that would
be easier to handle in a Google doc so that
we can have some sort of confirmation from
people um as we saw in response to your
email not everyone responded um promptly
or at all and so if we don't have a response
from an email it's hard to confirm that sort
of consensus that we were talking about but
in general I do agree that we don't need to
be fearful of sending emails to each other as
long as we do document them all in a public
way so if we have a deadline
of approving an agenda a week
before the meeting and it's all
on a Google Drive that's publicly
available I mean we can set that deadline and if
we get five responses or seven responses that's
the deadline so it's each person's responsibility
if they want to weigh in to CU we can always
abstain from voting in any you know during a
meeting or any time so if we just kind of set up a
process that we're building out the agenda and we
and the everybody approves it the week beforehand
and if somebody says Hey I want to invite X person
to do this and we have a single person say I don't
want them there then they just can't be on the
agenda and we can have that discussion during
the next meeting and Hammer it out does that
seem fair as a process yeah that makes sense
that that makes sense I I think the the thing
that I was thinking about with in specifically
regarding Ali Hill I was um remembering what we
had come up with in our recommendation that like
we would not specifically like we wouldn't um
it said that we'll work collabor ly to evaluate
potential partners and to come up to an agree with
an agreement with what sources will be considered
reliable and so I felt like that was jumping the
gun by like inviting her to come present because
we all hadn't talked and collaborated and agreed
that she would be a an appropriate partner so I
think it was it's the the substantive matter or
that she was being invited for but I think you're
right like if that's something that he puts on
an agenda then I could say that right and so
then we could talk about at the next meeting
so I think process-wise I think you're what
you're sugges makes sense but I just wanted to put
that out there because we did make that agreement
earlier the the deadline to have a
agenda did maybe I heard us talking
about the agenda I didn't hear we had
a deadline line is that a new thing or
was that discussed we're proposing that
David so that we do have a structure four
agendas for both this committee and for the
subcommittee so if we have a week before the
meeting will be the deadline to submit
items to the agenda on the on the share
drive and to contest anything on
there a week before the meeting to
add to the agenda and to contest anything yes okay
I guess we should put it out there how
does everyone feel about that having a
shared agenda and you have to the
week before the meeting to add or
contest anything on the agenda
is everyone comfortable with
that yes I am at
least Joe gayen David yes I'm comfortable with
it and this is for all meetings for all meetings
yes David gayen are you okay
with that or what are your
thoughts it works for
me the
uh I'm I'm just sorry I'm thaning through the
right Aldo um you know we we don't have our
other worker I guess Aldo does the best he can
to get him here um adalo you know sometimes is
there is he like we're we're we're kind of
playing this in some ways it's a like they
our own rules and we we decided to do this by
consensus and that and now we're like well you
know this guy and a week before and some people
are engaged and you know well nobody answered
the emails like I don't know maybe we're just
getting too deep into the Weeds on some you
know like we're we're trying to rewrite Robert's
books of rules or something in like some kind of
odd way and uh make make rules for ourselves
that may maybe are going to get in our own way
at some point but uh yeah take that for what
it's worth I think it's it's just kind of a
a silly thing to say that that's our Rule and
right if you know if I the day before the day
of the agenda I see something on the agenda
and I say oh well I don't like that you know
well you didn't say it a week before you know I
and then I say well I don't like we shouldn't be
doing this by consensus anymore we should you
know change the structure and this should be
done by like I don't I don't know what rights
I have to do that we don't have like a bylaws
like well I mean we just kind of get along
and uh so it it seems somewhat silly to to
kind of I call it hamstring ourselves but if
that's what you guys want to do it's fine with
me do you have another suggestion
my my suggestion is what it was I you know last
time and maybe even the time before I'm just so
frustrated that we we have nothing to work
with um and I think the only the only way to
get around this is is I and I don't again politics
are not my strong point but we need to have a bill
written or the governor has to do something to
change what we're doing here to make if if the
legislature and the administration think what
we're doing here is important they have to act
and treat us like that and no offense to Christina
or Aldo but like we we need facilitators we need
uh somebody okay this is how we're going to
operate and you know these are the members and
we're going to use Robert's Book of Rules and
we're gonna we're g to have resources and we
heard you and you said you need data we're going
to figure out how to get data and we're you know
it it's kind of just like throw us in the room to
make it look good you know um politically look we
created this group but now we can ignore them we
don't we don't need uh them and this I I've kind
of talked around to to different people and it's
a very very common situation what we are dealing
with very very common for this type of thing
to occur and appease of a societal you know
political facade of look what we we care about
get a bunch of people together and waste their
time and then you know eventually we all get
disinterested or fed up and quit or whatever
and then and then it just kind of tapers off and
and so I I'm really looking for that engagement
from somebody where there's there's money
there's uh facilitation and it takes all
of this stuff that we're talking about and you
know makes our work useful and and beneficial
and and everybody knows that it's going to be be
that at the end so that that's my suggestion but
who who writes that bill or does the governor
say I'm going to you know we're going to redo
this or this is what I I don't know who and how
that all happens but as of right now we don't
we don't have the structure behind us the Mandate
behind us to be able to work effectively my that's
my I what I believe is the solution and with my
lack of experience in politics is probably wrong
but Dave I served on on a local level for
five years I also did work with the state
legislature and your perception is 100% correct
and I think I brought up similar concerns that
the legislature say we did our job we're
done um that is the way politics work and
I don't care if you're talking about the town of
Palisade Mesa County the state leg legislature on
up they tend to they tend to pass something pass
it off to the legislative branch of government
and ignore it after that so I understand your
frustration and I'm happen I I'm very similar with
David and being frustrated the way this was set
up I'm still hopeful it can be changed to where
it's a little more meaningful um I personally
believe a lot of damage was done by this bill
it was some good done too it would be nice to see
it changed and to be something better um personal
perception but if there's not a way to engage or
if the different subcommittees that oversee this
aren't interested then yeah we're wasting our
time so David I do understand your frustration
completely well I think for the role of this
committee with the authority
we have through Senate Bill
2187 in a lot of
ways our best opportunity right now is to
figure out ways that we can most effectively
work especially within you know the Restraint
of sunshine laws to as what they call gather and
analyze data and other information regarding
wages and working conditions of a workers um
as effectively as possible and I I certainly
understand the frustration of uh things around
AG labor and the wheels of democracy in general
um being somebody that works on it every day
too uh but I think for today the best thing we
can do is come up with some ways that we aren't
hamstring ourselves and we aren't being efficient
and maybe having a rule of one week ahead of time
will slow us down but that's kind of I think the
discussion at hand is how can we best fit within
Sunshine laws and part of the where I was coming
from with this was I felt a little um ignorant
as far as what all we can do ahead of time and
I want to make sure I'm living up to being the
of responsibility for me being a coach a and
then also how we kind of can build some work
outside of our meetings that is compliant so maybe
it's not a week ahead of time maybe it's two days
ahead of time but I do think from what I remember
we actually have to have this posted yes publicly
before the meeting so we do have to set some
type of deadline from what I understand of the
rules so yeah maybe a week is two much
is it though for inviting speakers yeah
people's attendance that are you know
coming I think if we cut it down it's
just like have a hold on your calendar
but maybe you're not going to come yeah
that's true if this trly is bidding you know
Sunshine as far as the public being able to
see what we do there's no reason why we
can't work off this document throughout
the month right right in between meetings
right as long as it's publicly available
so so okay so the is the The Proposal so there's
a draft agenda out there or the the agenda for all
meetings is out there the proposed agenda people
can add to that agenda and then if if somebody
has suggests a topic for the agenda or a speaker
for the agenda and another member of the committee
does not agree with that they say that somehow
on the agenda like as a comment yes and then
when that happens if somebody is not in agreement
with that particular to uh topic or speaker then
that it doesn't necessarily become an agenda item
like that it becomes an agenda item for discussion
I guess right it or or it or it just doesn't make
the agenda we can have a space in the agenda for
contested agenda items and then talk about it at
the meeting and then if there can be consensus
for the next meeting then it makes it on the next
agenda so obviously that that speaker wouldn't be
invited to that meeting but the discussion of
whether that's going to take place would have
a place on the agenda it seems like yeah I mean
maybe I guess you're right doesn't doesn't have
to be because to me it allows some level of
consensus without anybody totally trying to
steer the you know the direction of the group
based on our own personal point of view and
it still allows for open discussion maybe it's
a month delayed but okay yeah I think the goal
is to set up that structure and that process for
these meetings so I think that's that's fair what
you're proposing and I will and David responding
back to your thoughts too there's no reason why
in this year's recommendations we can't say hey
we believe that there needs to be a statutory
chain to provide more support for this committee
to do its work it doesn't it doesn't matter what
we say in the report Dan nobody's reading it well
that's what we're trying to figure out who cares
what we write send them a blank piece of paper
send them of the text of Crime and Punishment do
right it doesn't matter what we say in the report
it is not valued it is useless the time and money
that we are all putting into this including our
our taxpayers to have Christina sit here to have
Aldo sit here to have Eric sit here is all wasted
no one is using what we are doing here well I
agree that it's only as valuable as how it is
used this is a public document we do have the
power to request a hearing that is something that
we could request also this is a public document
that can be used by anybody Farmers Union project
protect cfga Joe citizen can use this to Advocate
at the legislature to create change outside
this committee and so that's where I guess
you know hopefully that's not me but hopefully
somebody can can do that right that's I guess
that's you that's Rocky Mountain Farmers Union I
don't know who that is but uh thanks for making
me feel slightly better that it's not completely
useless but it's only you know like 1% useful uh
now you know I you you get my point like thank
you you're you're right you know and you know
we're doing good work we're trying but it it's
just not it's not rewarding it's not you know
we're not we've got to get somewhere and if
if that means we got to go to Daniels and I
remember you know talking with her about 2187
and saying you know she's like well one day
maybe you'll need me and and I you know I don't
really appreciate her and and but maybe I've got
to go to her and say you know you we need this
can you write this bill you know and i' I've
been you know I've blame Senate leadership for
the way they let it go and how you know and kind
of where we are and I'm trying to think what do
we do and how do we fix this and I'm with gayen
like how can we get out of the Trap and into the
to the you know something meaningful the drought
task force I think is our Prime contemporary thing
that we can use to show the the legislature the
administration like look what you did there
and look what you're doing here and there is
legislation being written right now or proposed or
whatever because of the work of the drought task
force there is none there is
nothing going on because of what we
did nobody cared nobody said oh we got to get
these people data can't do their work without
data well I appreciate you sharing
your opinion because you're right
I don't think any of us want to fall in the
Trap of just spending what is it 24 hours a
year together in addition to any side work
and have it not go anywhere so I do agree
that we do need to have discussions about how
to make this an effective tool um across the
board David I hear you and I appreciate your
position I think we've all been frustrated one
time or another because I know even as co-chair
I have to concur with what Dan said earlier as a
co-chair and not having with the restrictions
of the Sunshine Law we're having to maneuver
around that and it's been it's been a challenge
and um I'll accept that on for on my behalf but
I think moving forward given the time it's 11:19 I
think we should probably talk about you brought up
Ali Hill I would think this is the perfect time
we did request for additional data let's start
asking those presenters to come and meet with this
committee and share information um that was one of
the recommendations that we have speakers we have
to we have to agree that that they're credible or
that we're all comfortable with that David you
brought Ali Hill and I think Joe you also you
also advocated to have her come and present to
this group correct Joe yes I did and uh I agree
uh with all that you know Rome wasn't built in a
day drought data is you've had you know 10 to 20
years worth of data we don't have any and as time
goes along and data starts coming in and and this
thing starts to come together I think uh we have
to be a little more patient um uh just the way
I kind of feel about it but yeah I'm up for Ali
Hill and uh whoever else may come in uh whether
whether whatever Viewpoint or expert we can get
uh to supply data and as time goes on we'll put
that together and hopefully be able to relay that
in person to the ACT committee which Danielson
sits on and um maybe we can make a difference that
way I also agree with Dan on the public comment I
know uh a lot of uh producers uh paid attention
to uh what was put out in the C cfga newsletter
uh it wasn't much but there was a link to the
document and I know a lot of people read it
so uh on either side or whatever side there there
might be out there so I think information of what
we're doing here is is uh getting out there and
uh we've been able to build some bridges here and
that uh to me speaks uh miles uh in progress uh
compared to where we were before it all started
uh and where we are now personally I think uh
I feel a lot better about it I'm glad to be
here so can we get consensus that we would like
at Ali Hill at our next meeting and then maybe
down the road have another presenter come
to provide information and the reason I'm
saying that is so that we can get her on the
agenda and someone can reach out and invite
her for our next meeting but let's have
that discussion I am certainly in favor
of inviting her um she's solid academic
record um I reached out to her about the
study already and she was at least willing
to answer some of my probing questions um
but I think it would be good to have her at a
meeting so we can really discuss everything in
detail you comment um well if we're gonna invite
somebody with um with that type of background I
mean I would rather invite Phil Martin who's um
has way more experience than Ali Hill in this
area um but I I mean I guess either one is fine
I'm just trying to confirm whether are we talking
about at the next quarterly the meeting as a
whole like this entire group or because that
particular study was talking about the wages
right that study was I mean I know she's done
other studies and looked into other other issues
but and as Phil Martin as well um and so I would
suggest Phil Martin but I would also wanted
to clarify like what we inviting them to talk
about because they do have they look at a lot
of different things so if we're talking labor
conditions we're talking wages then maybe it
should be to that particular subcommittee can
we do both inite both of them this isn't an either
or Jennifer by any means and and uh I feel like um
I I I see this happen with uh politics like where
the president can't meet with somebody because
it might look bad or whatever um my take is is
invite you know without wasting all of our time
but invite everyone and let's build relationship
Rapport Bridges whatever you will um I don't know
who Phil Martin is but sounds like I need to no I
mean he's her predecessor I think he's her Mentor
I think he trained her you know is is what I'm
looking for is Ally can you help our committee
understand better how to fill the holes can we
work with you are you um able to help us answer
questions and and get her in front of everyone
so everyone can say well I don't trust her or
even if she does get us an answer it's no good um
and the same thing would be with with Phil Martin
or anyone but the the the idea is to get them
here and hear them out listen to them and see
what they're they're able to offer us Ali Hill may
not come like we it's great to say oh yeah doesn't
mean she has time or she cares or feel the same
thing or anyone but um I in my mind I like what's
it hurt to to have her come talk about her a labor
statistic uh California thing that we all talked
about and get a better understanding of what it
what it can mean or what it can't mean Etc we
don't have to put that in our report right that I
don't think just because she came to a Mee doesn't
mean Ali Hill reported that workers are getting
their wages cut you know in California and that's
what you know that like we don't I don't think we
have to be scared of something like that it's just
simple information gathering Rapport building and
right yeah no I'm just trying to I think we need
to clarify what the ask is because they they do a
lot and so that's why I was trying to confirm for
myself are we asking them to come to this meeting
as a whole like when this this group meets us
these quarterly meetings or the subcommittees and
and what are we asking them to come to talk about
is it like California so that's what I think we
need to we need to all be on the same page about
before we ask oh I don't know if it seems like
it'd be the same for committee or uh subcommittee
uh either one I mean we always discuss the same
things anyway at either one so and we're all there
so might as well just let's do it you know ASAP
so we get the ball rolling a little bit faster
I supp but I'd be willing to hear from both of
them I would propose that we invite Ali to speak
specifically to that report that she released
as far as overtime pay impacts across the a
industry in California and then any other Insight
that she can provide as far as potential overtime
impacts to the a sector in Colorado and that's
impact to workers and employers and competition
between states and everything else that they
might be able to provide and if Phil has Insight
I absolutely support even broadening it since it
sounds like he has a more established breath of
research so what if we had Ally at the wage
subcommittee and then had bill at the or we
invite both I mean they're both really busy
neither of them are focused in Colorado anymore
I mean I know Ali worked really closely with
Adrien card for a while um but I know I don't
think she's in Colorado anymore and so we could
invite both and see which one of them comes or I
mean I think I agree I think it makes sense to
just invite them to the to the meeting to the
group as a whole that to get a sense of what kind
of data they do have access to and to ask those
questions of them I mean they're economists
right and so I think that we could ask those
questions to either one of them and that cover
kind of all of our the labor conditions and wage
stuff and then they can kind of let us know what
they have okay and letting them know right the
the the reason I think we're inviting them is
like prompted it was this the the articles that
they've been doing on overtime but I'm sure that
they have other information to share I would um
say that we we may have to um it work around
their schedules if we care um or you know if
we're we're desperate um they you know they may
not fit our scheduling and if we value what they
have to say and want to hear them we might have to
have another meeting or or allow them to say well
this is when I'm available and I'd be happy to
meet with your group and and get that set up and
maybe make it an extra meeting um outside of our
kind of standing meetings um Andor be nimble in in
the the committee split meetings to maybe uh say
okay we're gonna have some invitees th this day
and we're gonna take the first 20 or 30 minutes
and so instead of having an hour each committee it
turns into 40 minutes each committee um with a you
know 40 minutes in the beginning for something but
uh so we heard about inviting both Bill and
Ally to either subcommittee or a the full board
committee is everybody okay with with inviting
both I mean I think it's a great idea yeah to be
clear I was just saying invite both to see if if
one or the other could come but not both of them
at the same time because well I mean I don't
I I just because Phil's like the guru of like
ad labor economics like that's my understanding
right and Ally I think is is newer and she worked
under him or she studied under him and so I was
saying you know he may not be available but she
might be or vice versa but but that's that was
the reason I was throwing it out there because
of their schedules and because we have these
time frames but but yeah I mean maybe they're um
I don't know if we need them both I think
we probably just need one of them but
um but the chances of getting one of them
might be better we just survive both so well
here's the thing that bothers me alli's study
is an actual study done through very credible
definitely not right-wing definitely leftwing
School of economics in California and yet she
still came up with results she came up with I
don't know if Phil's currently doing any actual
research on the on the modern condition that's
going on I don't know that he isn't either um
I'd rather hear about an actual study then I
would hear about an opinion that is based on
something that wasn't tried until recently I also
know there's studies going on in Oregon there's
study going on in Washington and one in New York
that I don't know when they'll come out or if they
ever do come out Washington has a nasty habit of
squashing things they don't like what they say um
I would prefer Ali that's an actual study and it's
pray reviewed it's published it's not an opinion
let me put it to you that way it's an actual study
it has more validity in my mind and I don't know
anything about Phil but I haven't seen anything
come I've seen Ali study come across peer review
haven't seen anything about Phil ever come across
in peer review so I that's my concern I still it
might be great to have him come he probably has
Insight that I don't have I think we ought to have
both what if we invite them we give we
send an invitation to both Ally and to
Phil and give them the three dates of
our regular subcommittee meetings and
our schol board meeting to see what
date they're available and then we
could accommodate their schedule with those
that would be my recommendation see who's
available yeah yeah yeah if if we need
to set a special meeting based on their
schedule we'll work together and figure
out a time and I think they work closely
enough together that they'll probably decide
like figure out like who schedule or who's
best to speak on it too you know who has more
relevant current knowledge or whatever so we
all have to be in agreement is everybody
online okay with that proposal yes from
Hunter yes who's going to do that the
committee chairs or who's going to contact
him Hunter you're always our Workhorse since
you've been in touch I I I'm happy yeah I can
reach out to them um thank you you have the I was
gonna I was gonna I mean I could too because I've
been in touch with Phil Martin and her but if
you want yeah I certainly don't want to and I
would be sort of cold calling Phil so if you
have a relationship with him that works well
for me that well there you go but unless she
come from the chairs though like you're the
chair of a committee it's to the it's to the
full committee meeting right either whatever
they're available okay so Jennifer will
take on that thank you y we got something
accomplish I I suppose Jennifer has to upload her
email to the thing so she to them and say we want
you to come be on this committee and she's doing
the work of the committee and that's all subject
to how do I do that she from what I understand she
only needs to if she's including another Committee
Member yeah she can do any independent work
well she's doing the work of the committee right
yeah it's about communication between community
members so yeah agreed and it's also logistical
so I wouldn't see a need to here okay well if
you guys want I can do that I can put my email
and her their response yeah I mean that's fine I
don't think it's required yeah don't need I I'm
looking to kind of understand these rules better
and so if if that's out that's great thank you
Christina not necessary for
me to be clear like I'm not
I'm fine with it not if if it doesn't have to
be do
we that covers speak for the next meeting
is there anything else I I think we covered
everything on our agenda we do have at least
a speaker for the next one hopefully for the
next meeting anything else any any anyone
would like to cover before we adjourn
today I think my hope is that over the next
three weeks we will each individually kind
of look at the recommendations we brought
forward last year and populate um the draft
agendas um for for things that can
be discussed during the subcommittee
meetings um I would like us to continue
to look at the fair food program I don't
know if we can invite somebody from
there to talk a little bit uh at some
point do you think that would be more appropriate
for working conditions wages for full committee
man they kind of cover everything uh
yeah I I just think it is good for all
of the people here to get exposed to the work
they're doing and um I get my thought is um
that my farm is a fair foods uh certified
farm and uh uh as it relates to wages and
working conditions on farms they're coming
and interviewing is a rigorous process that
is designed to eliminate coerced responses
and ensure that worker voices are being
they're they're authentic and they're real
which is a big concern of this um group of
the the situation and so it's a in my mind
it it I perceive it as a silver bullet for
producers and labor Advocates to um have Real
Results um in in improving conditions where
abuses are happening and giving um you know the
producers who are are good producers the p on
the the back and the clout that they deserve to
be recognized as good employers um and and so I
think if we could if we could dig into that you
know maybe our committee would would recommend
the state look into something or you know
I don't know what where it could lead but
I I I am a believer that it's a um a way to avoid
nasty policy legislation things yet have positive
impacts on worker conditions so David I think
i' probably propose we kind of follow the same
line of thinking we did with Ally and Phil is
we would invite somebody from the organization
it probably either be judge Laura Greg asbed
or the person the they've hired for Colorado
I'm assuming and let them choose who they feel
would be the best representative um would we
want to try to put that in the next subcommittee
meeting or would we want to put that in the next
full committee meeting in three months or do
we just do Betty three dates and navigate it
you you're the masters of the agenda the sooner
the better for me right we I mean there's a lot
of work to be done the sooner the better I think
it's important I think it's a you know but but
ultimately that's that's why you and Betty are
chairs and I'm not do you have contact with them
yeah I'll I'll if it's okay with folks I'll
reach out to them does anybody have a problem
if I do I would just Al also encourage you to
try to get someone from their auditing team
to attend um I was able to speak with them and
I feel like they they were sort of doing that
verification process that David described
um and I think they can speak to it in good
detail okay everybody okay with that yes um and
also just as a point of information for all of
you and anybody listening to this recording
or tuned in right now um we are organizing a
breakout session at the CFB GA conference um I
believe on the 27th of February and it it is a
social responsibility worker driven or worker
driven social responsibility programs we'll
have a representative from the fair food program
we'll have a representative from the Equitable
food initiative we'll have a representative
from USDA one of the two people that created
the farm labor stabilization pilot program that
was recently released and I I'm currently still
looking for potential a representative from
uh a worker Union if anybody has any contacts
um I think we're a little lean in Colorado but
um if it's either somebody from flock or from
United Farm Workers um would be I would love
to be in touch with them to kind of round out a
panel I wish I could help but I don't have any
contacts with those folks sure yeah I mean I just
have flocker you but and I might reach out I don't
think there's anybody else either and I know it's
not a workers but there's probably connections
with you United commercial food workers as well
as aflc you know they're all kind of in the same
famili so yeah right guess jobs Justice jobs with
Justice probably maybe yeah what was his name
jobs with Justice oh job of Justice yeah Sophia
thank
you does anybody else have anything else for for
today I just want to note that I made the draft
agendas for the next two subcomittee sets of
subcommittee meetings and the full advisory
committee meeting so if anybody wants to add
anything or any suggestions those are available
in the this folder already thank you Hunter for
doing that um I just wanted to know um I know was
not here today so maybe today's not the best day
for this conversation but um facilitating our
meetings to be mindful of The Interpreter and
allowing for um like valuable participation in
Spanish just because I think we go really quickly
and I'm also guilty of this um so just something
to know and maybe we can check in with other if
we can make it next meeting okay well yeah and
I I wonder also if that's maybe I have no idea
but like I'm wondering is is that maybe a reason
why yeah it's like yeah he has ad minutes is as
president you know he's pretty vocal because yeah
I know him separately and he's very vocal right
and so I I I wonder if yeah if there's a reason
like the lack of being able to fully participate
has impacted his um just prioritization yeah of
these meetings as you know seeing it as being
important enough for where he has a voice so
it could be like that whole circular problem
thank you for that reminder we'll be mindful
good point I'm G to reach out to him too wait
can I I can reach out to him about logistics
about coming I think so right okay Logistics
okay anything else anybody online
have anything else to share
Christina good luck best of luck to you oh yes
you yeah7 we're getting close congratulations
yes congratulations we appreciate all your
support Eric we look forward to working with
you thank you thank you Alo for coordinating
us I think with that we can adjourn the meeting
sounds good have a good rest of your day
good rest of your week bye all bye bye
I think we've got some things accomplish